so we will have a running example of how
the Tomaso algorithm works so whenever
we do something kind of to explain it we
will also show how it works so this is
an example of how the issue is working
first this is going to be our issue Q
I'm showing four instructions here this
is the first instruction this is the
second one third one and so on so we
will issue in program order which means
the first instruction that we're going
to be issue is going to be this F2 = F4
+ fub1 this is really an ad but I'm
writing it this way cuz it's more common
next for each of the floting point
registers which we are going to name
fub1 F2 F3 and F4 there is a register
Alias table or rat where we're going to
keep which instruction is supposed to
produce that register if there is
nothing here that actually points to the
register file so pretty much if there is
nothing here in F1 that's going to mean
that you can just find the value for F1
in the actual F1 in the register file
this is our register file we have four
registers and these are the their actual
values when we go through the example we
will actually compute with them so again
this is the register file again the rat
when it's empty says that basically this
means F1 can just be read from the
register file you don't have to wait for
anything and finally we're going to have
a reservation stations we're going to
name them rs1 2 3 for the ad reservation
stations and four and five for the
multiplication reservation station so we
really have five reservation stations
but note that you can use only these
three for ads and only these three for
multiplies divides now we are ready to
actually issue an instruction so again
this is going to be the first one we
issue the first step is to take it from
the instruction buffer the next step is
to look at the rat and find whether our
inputs are ready or not and in this case
both of the inputs are ready F1 and F4
are both
available so we're going to say that
this is an ADD
and we're going to take the value for in
this case F4 and F1 and that's going to
be
0.71 and it's going to be 3.14 and place
the instruction in the reservation
station of course that assumes that
there is a reservation station available
we will see eventually what happens when
there isn't any and the final step for
register naming is to say that the
result of the instruction F2 is going to
come from now on from reservation
station one so here we will write
rs1 so future instructions that want F2
are not going to read minus one they're
going to wait for this result to be
produced so this is the renaming of the
very first instruction one final step
that we will do of course is remove this
instruction from the issue queue and
what's going to happen now is this is
going to shift down but for my example
that's going to be very difficult to do
so I'm just going to kind of cross out
this instructions so this is this just
means that you know this instruction has
been removed from the issue Cube
to make things more interesting for
remaining instructions and also to see
what happens when an instruction is
renamed let's issue one or two more
instructions so let's issue the next
instruction which is this one this is a
divide we need to find a free
reservation station here say it's a
divide F2 and F3 are going to be the
parameters for this instruction F2 comes
from rs1 so we cannot simply read this
value here we're going to say here that
rs1
is what we're waiting for but F3 is
available so we're going to get
2.72 from the register F and we now Mark
this instruction as we're going to
basically take it out of the issue q and
this is so very easy to forget but when
we do that we need to mark that the
result the F1 is from now on not going
to be coming from here it's going to be
coming from reservation station 4 and
we're going to issue this instruction
two it's a subtraction so it's going to
go here fub1 and FS2 are the
parameters we see that neither of those
two can be read from the register file
so what we're going to do is we're going
to Mark here that that the first
parameter is going to be produced by RS4
the second one is going to be produced
by
rs1 we're going to then Mark that F4 is
coming from
rs2 and we're going to remove this
instruction from the isq of course more
instructions are probably going to come
this way but we're not going to look at
that because again that that too many
instructions for this example now let's
say that there wasn't an issue slot here
we then couldn't issue the next
instruction in the next cycle until we
are actually done executing one one of
these two I'm not going to do that but
just just keep in mind that when you
want to issue an instruction you first
have to check whether a reservation
station is available if not then we
simply cannot issue that in ruction
let's issue it now because we do have
room for it it's an addition of FS2 and
fs3 F2 comes from reservation station
one F3 comes from the register file so
we're just going to take the
2.72 we're going to then rename F1 to
point to this result and now we see that
F1 is already renamed to reservation
station 4 that's
basically if you want to use F1
since this instruction you would be
waiting for its result but now F1 is
being basically renamed to another
reservation station so this is how
register naming here Works in tomasulo's
algorithm so what we're going to do is
we're going to basically overwrite this
with the name of this reservation
station which is
RS3 and now we have issued all of our
four instructions in a real
processor you would issue one
instruction each cycle and probably some
of this instructions would have executed
by the time we issue all of them but I
just wanted to show you how issue works
if for example nothing could execute for
some reason now that we have gone
through an example of issuing let's see
what the next step is